<?xml version="1.0"?> 
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY appname "MOFsim">
<!ENTITY app "<application>MOFsim</application>">
<!ENTITY appversion "0.1.0">
<!ENTITY manrevision "0.1.0">
<!ENTITY date "August 2011">
]>
<article id="index" lang="en">
  <articleinfo><title>&appname; Manual</title>
    <abstract role="description">
      <para>&app; is a program for accessing Finite Difference Time Domain (FDTD) analysis of microstructured fibre designs.</para>
    </abstract>
    <copyright>
      <year>2011</year>
      <holder>Paul Childs</holder>
    </copyright>
    <author role="maintainer">
      <firstname>Paul</firstname>
      <surname>Childs</surname>
      <affiliation>
        <orgname>University of New South Wales</orgname>
        <address>
          <email>pchilds@physics.org</email>
        </address>
      </affiliation>
    </author>
    <revhistory>
      <revision>
        <revnumber>&appname; Manual &manrevision;</revnumber>
        <date>29-08-2011</date>
      </revision>
    </revhistory>
    <releaseinfo>
      Version &manrevision; documenting &appname; version &appversion;.
    </releaseinfo>
    <legalnotice><title>Copyright</title>
      <para>Copyright (C)  2011  Paul Childs.</para>
      <para>Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this document under the terms of the GNU Free Documentation License, Version 1.3 or any later version published by the Free Software Foundation; with no Invariant Sections, no Front-Cover Texts, and no Back-Cover Texts. A copy of the license is included in the section entitled "GNU Free Documentation License".</para>
    </legalnotice>
  </articleinfo>
  <sect1 id="introduction"><title>Introduction</title>
    <para>Use &app; to visually create a .ctl file for running FDTD simulations. Position circles and assign materials to design the layout of the microstructured fibre. A wide range of material types such as anisotropy and nonlinearity are supported.</para>
    <para>For updates please visit <ulink type="http" url="https://github.com/pchilds/MOFsim">MOFsim's repository</ulink></para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="frp"><title>The Front Panel</title>
    <para>&app uses the principle of layers to design microstructured fibres. Each layer is assigned a material, geometry and positioning parameters. Layers placed later on overlay earlier layers and thus the property at any point is determined by the latest layer that makes use of that point (e.g. a small cylinder of air placed after and within a larger cylinder of silica acts as a hole drilled through the silica -- note that if the air layer was placed first it would have no effect, so make sure you plan ahead the ordering of placement).</para>
    <para>For the case of placing arrays additional positioning parameters are available. Pitch controls the nearest neighbour spacing in the arrays, and azimuth the relative angle on the display. When you are satisfied with the positioning of your layer press &quot;Add/Update&quot; to place the layer and move on to another potential layer.</para>
    <para>Spatial units are in terms of microns. If the design doesn't fit well with the current size of the display or is otoo small, the display can be zoomed by making use of the two zoom boxes in the top right corner. The second box selects whether to zoom in (arrows pointing out) or zoom out (arrows pointing in). The first box selects whether to perform a single click zoom (an X in the box), zoom by dragging over a rectangle (a dashed box) or not zoom at all (blank) allowing the user to interact with the diagram.</para>
    <para>At any time you can swap to another layer by clicking on it in the diagram (provided the first zoom box is blank), however changes made on your current layer will be lost unless you first click on &quot;Add/Update&quot;</para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="mnu"><title>The Menus</title>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="xmpl"><title>Examples</title>
    <sect2><title>Example 1: Solid Core fibres</title>
      <para>Create a new material called &quot;Substrate&quot; and give it an appropriate dielectric value. Change the radius to the desired size and press &quot;Add/Update&quot;. Select &quot;Air&quot; as the next material and &quot;Hexagonal Array minus centre&quot; as the geometry. Select the desired radius, pitch and number of rings for the holes. Press &quot;Add/Update&quot; and then File->Save.</para>
      <para>Pick a frequency as 1 divided by the wavelength in microns (e.g. 1550nm corresponds to 0.6452 in meep units), press File->Run and then select your previously saved file.</para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2><title>Example 2: Hollow Core fibres</title>
      <para>Create a new material called &quot;Substrate&quot; and give it an appropriate dielectric value. Change the radius to the desired size and press &quot;Add/Update&quot;. Select &quot;Air&quot; as the next material and &quot;Single Cylinder&quot; as the geometry. Adjust the radius to the value of the central hole and Press &quot;Add/Update&quot;.</para>
      <para>Select &quot;Hexagonal ring&quot; as the geometry and then select the desired pitch and radius of the holes and give the outer ring value (equal to the number holes on the outside of the hole region divided by 6). Add a few of these rings working inwards until a certain transition region where the rings change from hexagonally arranged to more circularly in order to match the centre core.</para>
      <para>At this point the holes need to be inserted individually (future releases may address a circular to hexagonal transition). When finished select File->Save. Pick a frequency, press File->Run and then select your previously saved file.</para>
    </sect2>
    </sect2>
    <sect2><title>Example 3: Infiltrated fibres</title>
      <para>Microstructured fibres with material infiltrated in their capillaries can be made in the same fashion as the above examples.</para>
      <para>If all capilaries are infiltrated then instead of air in the above example, use the material to be infiltrated. If the material forms a thin film then add an air layer after this, identical except in that the radius is smaller.</para>
      <para>If individual capillaries are infiltrated then simply add the infiltrated material as a new layer overlapping the air layer (with another air layer if the infiltrated material forms a thin film).</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
  <glossary>
    <glossdiv><title>F</title>
      <glossentry>
        <glossterm>FDTD</glossterm>
        <glossdef><para>Finite Difference Time Domain. A method for numerically solving Maxwell's equations. The differential equations are converted to difference equations in time. Although it has the advantage over eigenmode solvers as being able to solve for all wavelengths with the one simulation, it requires much more computation time -- particularly when small features (with respect to the entire structure) are present.</para></glossdef>
      </glossentry>
    </glossdiv>
  </glossary>
</article>
